MOHAMMAD SHAMIM AHSAN

+880 1765 102 940 | <u>shamim19119@gmail.com</u> <u>Website</u> | <u>GitHub</u> | <u>LinkedIn</u>

ABOUT ME

Want to explore and learn new things. Passionate about working on *Cyber security*, and aim to explore existing methods and invent new techniques in this field, including *machine learning* and *deep learning* algorithms. Always enjoy working with hard-working and enthusiastic people, and have a strong commitment to research.

EDUCATION

Bangladesh University of Engineering & Technology

Bachelor of Computer Science and Engineering

Department of Computer Science and Engineering

St. Joseph Higher Secondary School, Dhaka

July, 2015 – July, 2017

Higher Secondary Certificate (HSC)

Division of Science

GPA: 5.00/5.00 (90.3%)

Bangladesh Navy School and College, Chittagong

Secondary School Certificate (SSC)

WORK EXPERIENCE

Division of Science

Lecturer July, 2023 - Present

Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering (ECE)

Presidency University, Gulshan-2, Dhaka, Bangladesh

Undergraduate Research Assistant

Department of Computer Science and Engineering Bangladesh University of Engineering & Technology

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Bangladesh University of Engineering & Technology (BUET)

May, 2022 - Present

GPA: 5.00/5.00

2022 - 2023

Title: Detecting User Activity from Encrypted IoT Traffic

Undergraduate Research Assistant

Supervisor: Dr. Md. Shohrab Hossain **(BUET)**

Collaborator: Dr. Anupam Das (NC State University, USA)

- Implemented a methodology called "packet-based signature generation & detection system" for automatically extracting packet-level **signatures** from their network traffic and detecting events of smart home devices.
- Used **Java** at a large scale as the project **codebase** was in Java.
- Needed to write **Python**, **Shell-script** and **C++** programmes.
- Monitored network traffic using **Wireshark**.
- Used 4 datasets: PINGPONG, UNSW, YourThings, Mon(IoT)r.
- Outperformed the average recall and precision of the existing system.
- Worked as *first author*, contributed *significantly* in writing.

Bangladesh University of Engineering & Technology

January, 2023 - Present

Title: Randomization in Double Coverage Algorithm on a Line for Online *k*-Server problem *Undergraduate Research Assistant*

Supervisor: Dr. Md. Saidur Rahman (BUET) Collaborator: Dr. Abu Reyan Ahmed (Colgate University, USA)

- Studied **exact** algorithms, **approximate** algorithms, **randomized** algorithms, **online** algorithms, **heuristics** and **metaheuristics**, and **low memory** algorithms.
- Worked on the implementation of randomization techniques to find k-competitiveness on the well-known
 Double Coverage Line algorithm.
- Used the Potential Function Method and Interleaving Move Style for competitive analysis of the algorithms.

- Studied some algorithms in different metric spaces.
- Worked as *first author*, contributed *significantly* in writing.

ACADEMIC PROJECTS

Image Caption Generator using CNN and LSTM

February, 2023

Python, Flickr dataset

Github

Implemented an image caption generation architecture with **a team of 2 people** where I rolled as a **leader**. In this project,

- Recognized the context of an image and annotated it with relevant captions using deep learning methods.
- **CNN** was used to generate a vectorized representation of an image. Then, **LSTM** used the information from CNN to help generate a caption of the image.
- Implemented Greedy and Beam search strategies and evaluated our architecture using BLEU and METEOR metrics.

Spacey: Online Space Rental Platform

August, 2022

MongoDB, Express.js, Rest.js, Node.js, CSS

Github, Github, Demo

Created an online platform with **a team of 3 people** where property owners can rent their places or free spaces which helps travelers or business companies to find a home/storage to use. Also designed **BPMN**, **Mock UI** (using **Figma**), **Class**, **ER**, **Sequence**, and **Collaboration diagrams**. Main **modules** of the system were Search, Renting, Hosting, Bookings, Payment, Review-Rate-Complain, Chat, Profile. We used **Stripe** gateway for our mobile banking payment method.

TCP CERL: congestion control enhancement over wireless networks Network Simulator 3(NS3), C, Python

February, 2022

Github

In this project,

- Studied the **TCP-CERL** technique for enhancement of congestion control which is the sender-side modification of **TCP-Reno**.
- Implemented this technique in NS3. The implementation that the authors of the paper did was in NS2.
- Tested on two wireless networks: **Wi-Fi** and **LR-WPAN**. Then, calculated various **performance metrics** such as throughput, end-to-end delay time, delivery-ratio and loss-ratio.

Super Mario (Microcontroller project)

July, 2021

C, Atmel Studio, Proteus 8

<u>Github</u>

This is a Proteus **simulation-based** Microcontroller project. Developed a simple game similar to the super mario using **ATmega32**, **LED green Dot Matrix** and **LCD display**. To multiplex two LED matrices, we used the same port for the upper side of both LED's and two different ports for the lower sides of them.

MediSheba October, 2020

Django, HTML, CSS, Oracle SQL

Github, YouTube

Developed an online medical system with **a team of 3 people** where doctor, patient and blood-bank are the main **modules**. Django is used here as a framework in Back-end and HTML, CSS are used here as Front-end. The (oracle-based) database of the project was **designed extensively following the relevant ER diagrams**.

MAJOR ASSIGNMENTS

• SEED-LABS Attacks

July, 2022

Implemented some SEED-LABS attacks such as **Buffer overflow**, **CSRF**, **XSS**, **SQL injection** and **Morris worm**.

Github, Demo(CSRF), Demo(XSS), Demo(SQL Injection)

Bangla Handwritten Character Recognition using CNN

February, 2023

Designed own CNN model from scratch using python and tested on the **NumtaDB** dataset.

Github

PRESENTATIONS

• **Conference** presentation in IEEE Computer Society Bangladesh Chapter Summer Symposium 2023 **(IEEE CS BDC SS)**, **Topic:** Randomization in Double Coverage Algorithm on a Line for Online *k*-Server problem.

SKILLS

Languages C, C++, Java, Python, Shell script, JavaScript, SQL

Frameworks Django, React.js, Express, Node.js

DatabasesOracle, MongoDBWeb TechnologiesHTML, CSS, BootstrapOperating SystemsWindows, Ubuntu, WSLTechnical WritingLaTeX, Beamer, Overleaf

Others Git (GitHub), NS3, XV6, Docker, OpenGL, MS Word, MS Excel, MS PowerPoint

ACHIEVEMENTS

Dean's List Award, Bangladesh University of Engineering & Technology 2022- 2023

For outstanding academic performance in 4th year (with average GPA: 3.97/4.00)

Government Scholarship, Bangladesh 2017- 2022

For outstanding performance in Higher Secondary Certificate Examination

Region position: 83

Government Scholarship, Bangladesh 2015- 2017

For outstanding performance in Secondary School Certificate Examination

Region position: 135

College Final Examination 2016

Merit position: 1 (in whole college)

HIGHLIGHTED ACADEMIC COURSES

Undergraduate courses, Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology

CSE-321 Computer Networks
 CSE-405 Computer Security
 CSE-471 Machine Learning
 CSE-461 Algorithm Engineering
 CSE-423 Fault Tolerant Systems

• CSE-453 High Performance Database Systems

LANGUAGES

English	Bangla	Hindi
Professional Working Proficiency	Native	Listening & Speaking